Guide to the New-York Historical Society Museum Department Records 1765, 1830-2018 NYHS-RG 20
New-York Historical Society
- Series III. Curatorial and Administration Files, 1934-2016; 50.87 Linear feet
  - Subseries III.D. Holly Hotchner Files, 1970-1994; 15.08 Linear feet
    - Public Programs & Collections Access (23 folders), 1986-1992 (Offsite-box 129, Folder 1-23)
      Includes files concerning various public programs, including a slide show talk providing an overview of the collections (1986), publicity material for programs, summary lists, proposed visitor surveys, a study of visitor and member groups (1988), and a review of the use of museum collections and staff in education and research programs.
    - Special Events (13 folders), 1993-1994 (Offsite-box 130, Folder 1-13)
      Includes files concerning private uses of N-YHS's facilities, including for filming such as Robert Redford's Quiz Show and TV's Law and Order, and for meetings of Community Advisory Board 7, the Alliance for the Arts, and Bard College's Decorative Arts program symposium. The files also reference film rights for material, including for Florentine Films' series The Civil War.
    - Professional Activities and Miscellaneous (9 of 37 folders), 1984-1994 (Offsite-box 130, Folder 14-22)
      These files include documents related to N-YHS's and Hotchner's professional affiliations, such as with the Association of American Museums and sponsoring student studies at N-YHS, and Hotchner's professional activities outside of N-YHS, particularly in terms of lectures on conservation. There are also a small number of files on subjects that did not fit clearly into other categories.
    - Professional Activities and Miscellaneous (28 of 37 folders), 1978-1994 (Offsite-box 131, Folder 1-37)
  - Subseries III.E. Annette Blaugrund Files, 1989-1995; 2.63 Linear feet
    The subseries includes, at least in large part, the files of Annette Blaugrund, Senior Curator of Paintings, Drawing & Sculpture from 1989-1995. The files include correspondence concerning proposed exhibitions, research inquiries, offers of objects for accession, and other museum matters. The files also include object surveys, especially for sculpture, and general administration and exhibition planning documents. Fuller summaries of the content are provided in the container list below. Certain of Blaugrund's files are currently restricted. See the Access Restrictions note. A major initiative of Blaugrund's was the planning for an exhibition about the Tenth Street Studio Building. This subseries holds few or no files on the matter; the bulk of these were integrated at some point with other exhibition files. See Series II. Exhibitions, Subseries I. General Files, folders for Painting and Patronage: The Tenth Street Studios (1993).
    - General Correspondence & Memos (7 of 17 folders), 1991-1995 (Offsite-box 132, Folder 1-7)
      Includes correspondence and memos concerning incoming research inquiries about objects and artists, exhibition proposals, offers of objects, and other museum matters.
    - General Correspondence & Memos (10 of 17 folders), 1989-1995 (Offsite-box 133, Folder 1-10)
    - Administrative Files (4 folders), 1989-1994 (Offsite-box 133, Folder 11-14)
      Includes files concerning visitor counts, intern tasks, filing system, a museum brochure reference material, and facilities information, especially lighting recommendations for the second floor corridor gallery.
    - Collections Policies (4 folders), 1990-1994 (Offsite-box 134, Folder 1-4)
    - Exhibitions (7 of 11 folders), 1991-1995 (Offsite-box 134, Folder 5-11)
      Includes files on proposed exhibitions and planning meeting and procedures. One file includes notes concerning the Treasury of the Past (1995) exhibition and another concerns a long-term loan to the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation.
    - Exhibitions (4 of 11 folders), 1987-1995 (Offsite-box 135, Folder 1-4)
      Includes files on the Paris 1889: American Artists at the Universal Exposition and Rare Birds of China exhibitions, and a proposed Urban Gallery.
    - Research Sources (4 folders), circa 1991-1993 (Offsite-box 135, Folder 5-8)
      Includes notes and other documents identifying art research sources.
    - Object Descriptions & Inventories (11 of 13 folders), 1990-1994 (Offsite-box 135, Folder 9-19)
      Principally includes surveys and inventories of paintings and sculpture.
    - Object Descriptions & Inventories (2 of 13 folders), 1993 (Offsite-box 136, Folder 1-2)
      Includes a system-generated Sculpture Checklist as of April 15, 1993, by Ann Weissman.
  - Subseries III.G. Various Curatorial Files, 2002-2016; 5.5 Linear feet
    The subseries includes files transferred to the archives from the museum that were those of various curators, assistant/associate curators, contracted consulting curators, or others involved in developing exhibitions or shaping the collection scope and presentation. In many instances, the specific provenance of the files may not be clear and were included here because of the nature of the subject matter.
    Arrangement
    The files are loosely arranged and were generally retained as transferred to the archives.
    - Exhibition curatorial working files, circa 1996-2004 (Offsite-box 292)
      Primarily includes files from Mina Weiner, Jan Ramirez, Kathy Hulser, and Ellen Denker. Primarily concerns object lists, text, planning, programming, and the like for various exhibitions, including especially: Alexander Hamilton, Life on a Lapel, Family Matters, Jules Feiffer, Home Sewn, Bella Landauer: Collecting Enterprises, Revolutions, British in New York, the N-YHS Bicentennial in 2004. Includes some other planning documents, such as a Visible Storage Best Practices Analysis (1997).
    - Exhibition curatorial working files, 2002-2012 (Offsite-box 297)
      Files transferred to the archives in 2017. These files are primarily from the office of Museum Director Linda Ferber and relate to various exhibitions. These include AIDS, Armory Show, Historical Fictions, Legacies, Lincoln & New York, Finding Priscilla's Children, Audubon's Aviary, Ashcan Painters, Atlantic Revolutions, Grant & Lee, Clarice Lee, New York Divided, and a few other smaller files.
    - Exhibition curatorial working files, 2009-2010 (Offsite-box 298)
      Includes Marybeth de Filippis's file on "Dutch New York between East and West: The World of Margrieta van Varick (2009); binder and file on object conservation for the Great Hall (2010); binder of "100% Design Development with Exhibit Script and Exhibit Item Schedule" for the Dimenna Childen's Museum (2010); and proposals for a N-YHS web redesign by Mediatrope LLC and by Tronvig Group (2010).
    - Exhibition curatorial working files, 2008-2011 (Offsite-box 299)
      Includes files on the Cholera and the Insulin exhibitions.
    - Exhibition curatorial working files, circa 2009-2016 (Offsite-box 315)
      The box appears to hold exhibition-related files from Linda Ferber. Principal files concern: Coast & Sea, Making It Modern (Nadelman), Making American Taste, Beauty's Legacy, Clarice Smith, Swing Time (Reginald Marsh), and photographs of A New Light on Tiffany as exhibited at the Flagler Museum (2012).
    - Various curatorial files, circa 2012-2014 (Offsite-box 316)
      Includes a small set of Linda Ferber files, including those on the Hudson River School exhibition.
- Series IV. Collection Management Files, 1929-2008; 36.93 Linear feet
  The Collections Management series includes certain records of the Registrar and other records related to the administration of museum objects. The bulk of the series by far includes records of outgoing loans from N-YHS for exhibition or other display at other institutions; these loan records extend back to 1929. Though extensive, the loan records do not appear to include all outgoing loans.
  The series includes some records of incoming loans for some of N-YHS's exhibitions of the 1940s and 1950s. (The bulk of incoming exhibition loan records are found in Series II, Exhibitions.) This series also holds accession lists and receipts for the 1950s-1960s.
  The series also holds a few files from the 1980s-1990s covering the transport and warehousing of the collection at that time, as well as location mapping for the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture, which opened in 2000.
  The Collection Management series is organized in the following subseries:
  Subseries IV.A. Early Registrar Files
  Subseries IV.B. Outgoing Loans
  Subseries IV.C. Albina De Meio and Related Files
  Subseries IV.D. Luce Center Logistics
  Subseries IV.E. Conservation Surveys & Other Files
  Subseries IV.F. Incoming Loan and Other Exhibition-Related Files.
  Subseries IV.G. General Collections Management Files
  - Subseries IV.A. Early Registrar Files, 1929-1965; 1.83 Linear feet
    The subseries includes files from the Museum Registrar, roughly from the early years of the museum's establishment as a department (circa 1939) to the 1960s. These were principally Carolyn Scoon (1942-1957),Theresa Czajkowska (1950-1957), and Dorothy Hull (1958-1961). The files include receipts for outgoing loans by N-YHS, including early (1929-1938) records of such loans. Incoming loan files, as well as the explicitly labeled files for exhibitions, document objects borrowed for exhibition at N-YHS in the 1940s-1950s. The series includes registrar receipts for other objects, such as those submitted for consideration for donation. Accessions and auction sales are documented in the working files for the annual reports and elsewhere in the subseries.
    The subseries is arranged by subject matter and follows original order as found during processing in 2016.
    - Notes for Annual Reports, 1949-1962 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1962 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 2)
    - Draft Manual for Museum Registrars, 1954 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 3)
    - Imaging Service Fees, 1953 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 4)
    - Thompson Homestead Museum, East Hampton, L.I., 1942-1945 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 5)
    - Material Sold, 1943-1948 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 6)
      Includes books and museum objects sent to auction.
    - Registrar Receipts (4 folders), 1956, 1960-1962 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 7-10)
    - "Hall of Great Events", circa 1937 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 11)
    - Evacuation List, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous Museum Accessions, etc., circa 1939-1950 (Offsite-box 142, Folder 13)
    - Receipt Books #1 and #3 for Articles Given Out or Loaned by N-YHS, 1929-1933, 1936-1938 (Offsite-box 143, Folder 1)
    - Loans by N-YHS (5 folders), 1954-1957 (Offsite-box 143, Folder 2-6)
    - Loans by N-YHS (8 folders), 1957-1964 (Offsite-box 144, Folder 1-8)
    - Loans by N-YHS, 1965 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 1)
    - Indefinite Loans by N-YHS, 1945-1963 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 2)
    - Loans to N-YHS (2 folders), 1952-1960 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 3-4)
    - Indefinite Loans to N-YHS, 1939-1962 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 5)
    - Deposted Temporarily, 1942-1956 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 6)
    - Exhibition. Portraits of Americans by Americans, 1945 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 7)
    - Exhibition. American Presentation Silver, 1946-1947 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 8)
    - Exhibition. John James Audubon, 1946-1947 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 9)
    - Exhibition. Frederic Remington: Artist of the Old West, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 10)
    - Exhibition. Children's Portraits, 1948-1949 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 11)
    - Confederate Exhibition, 1949 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 12)
    - Exhibition. George Harvey, 1948 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 13)
    - Exhibition. Ezra Ames of Albany, Portrait Painter, 1955 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 14)
    - Exhibition. John James Audubon, 1963 (Offsite-box 145, Folder 15)
  - Subseries IV.B. Outgoing Loans, 1939, 1947, 1976-2005; 1976-2002; 20.21 Linear feet
    The Outgoing Loan Requests subseries of the New-York Historical Society museum records consists of files that were created within the Museum Department (likely by the registrar and associated staff) and chiefly relate to requests from outside institutions for loans of items from N-YHS's museum and library/print room collections for exhibition purposes. The date range for the series runs from 1975 to 2002.
    The types of materials contained in the files include: internal and external correspondence such as memoranda and letters, facility reports, research material, loan agreements, receipts, insurance certificates, shipping invoices, and condition reports. Additionally, some files include photographic prints, slides, transparencies, and negatives of requested items, requesting facilities, or of damage to requested items incurred in connection with loans. Some files include exhibition checklists or catalogues. Files holding such images or print matter are noted in the container list below.
    Together the materials document the considerations, process, and logistics underlying N-YHS's loan of particular objects, from initial request, review and recommendation by internal staff, final approval or rejection by the Board of Trustees, conservation work, insurance coverage, packing and shipment, and the resulting exhibitions and related publicity and press. More broadly, the files document the history of N-YHS's overall loan activities and the ways in which the collections have been called on in support of other institutions' exhibitions. Loans for purposes other than museum exhibitions are also documented, including long-term loans for display in government buildings.
    The subseries includes files not only for loan requests that were satisfied, but also for those requests that were declined, withdrawn, or otherwise unfulfilled. Some rejections or rescissions of loan requests in 1988, 1993, and 1999 reflect loan moratoria due to larger events in N-YHS's history, including inventorying of collections, financial difficulties, and an anticipated move of collections related to the opening of the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture, respectively.
    The Outgoing Loan Requests subseries is arranged chronologically by year of file. Within each year's set of files, there are typically multiple types of files depending on the lending department, whether the request was fulfilled or not, and so forth. When multiple file types were contained within a year, the files were arranged with those having a loan number appearing first. These appear to be only museum objects and the number was likely assigned during input of object information to TMS, the Museum Department's inventory database. These loan files are arranged sequentially, though there are gaps in the numbering.
    Following the files with loan numbers are those with no assigned loan number. These are arranged in the following order within a given year: long-term loans, museum loans, library loans, unfulfilled loans, loans of unknown resolution, and miscellaneous other types. Not all types are present in every year.
    Although documents were transferred to archival folders during processing, when the original folders contained significant writing or annotation, they were retained with the documents. Folder titles were devised by the processing archivist based on the original folder labels, handwritten annotations on the folders, or folder contents. For satisfied loan requests, the name of the borrowing institution is the principal element noted in the file label. Files relating to loan requests that were denied or withdrawn were combined into "unfulfilled loan" files by year, with no further detail in the container list.
    In some instances, the processing archivist found two or more folders relating to the same loan in the original files. These were likely the files of different museum staff (separate loan files maintained by the library staff are found with the library records) and so were generally merged, but materials were sleeved and original folders retained to indicate their separate origins. Materials found subsequent to processing the core of records were added to the container list in their proper order, but were not physically integrated; these files were instead placed in separate boxes appearing at the end of the subseries.
    - Long-term loan (1975): The Hispanic Society of America, 1981, 1987 (Offsite-box 1)
      Concerns a long-term loan of St. John the Baptist by Castillo y Saavedra from 1975 to 1987.
    - OLR-1976.2. Jersey City Public Library Museum (Offsite-box 1)
      Includes photographic print of the loaned object.
    - Library: High Museum of Art, 1976 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1977.1. The American Federation of Arts (Offsite-box 1)
    - Library: Eleutherian Mills Historical Library, 1977 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.1 Museum of American Folk Art (Offsite-box 1)
      Includes a photographic print of the requested item(s).
    - OLR-1978.2. National Collection of Fine Arts, Smithsonian (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.3. Old Dartmouth Historical Society Whaling Museum, 1978-1979 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.4. The Hudson River Museum (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.5. Coe Kerr Gallery (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.6. The Century Association (Offsite-box 1)
      Includes a photographic negative of the requested item(s).
    - OLR-1978.7. The Century Association (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.8. The Albany Institute of History and Art (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.9. Art Gallery of Nova Scotia, 1977-1979 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.10. High Museum of Art, 1977-1979 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.11. The Corning Museum of Glass, 1977-1978 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1978.12. Albany Institute of History and Art, 1972, 1978 (Offsite-box 1)
      Additionally includes a loan form for a 1972 loan of glass paperweights to the Albany Institute of History and Art.
    - Library: Beth Hatefutsoth, 1978 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1979.1. National Portrait Gallery, Smithsonian, 1978-1979 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1979.2. The Hudson River Museum, 1979, 1982 (Offsite-box 1)
      Includes a photographic print of the requested item(s). This folder additionally includes correspondence in 1982 regarding a loan of Asher B. Durand drawings and engravings.
    - OLR-1979.3. The Bronx Museum of the Arts, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1979.4. American Museum of Natural History (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1979.5. Amon Carter Museum, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1979.6. Robert Hull Fleming Museum, University of Vermont, 1978-1979 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1979.7. Fraunces Tavern Museum, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1979.8. The Brooklyn Museum, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 1)
    - OLR-1979.9. Cragsmoor Free Library, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 1)
      Includes photographic prints of the requested item(s).
    - OLR-1979.12. The Metropolitan Museum of Art (3 folders), 1939-1947, 1978-1993 (Offsite-box 48)
      Concerns a long-term loan of paintings from the Bryan Collection. Includes photographic prints and a color transparency of the requested item(s) and restoration reports from 1942 regarding paintings 1867.4 (B-4), 1867.6 (B-6), 1867.7 (B-7), and 1867.14 (B-14). Also included is correspondence with staff of the Rijksmuseum in 1939 and 1947 regarding identification of the subject of a painting (1867.182 (B-182)).
    - Museum: Bronx County Historical Society, 1979-1981 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Unfulfilled loans, 1979 (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1980.2. National Portrait Gallery, Smithsonian, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1980.3. National Portrait Gallery, Smithsonian, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1980.4. University of New Hampshire, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1980.5. National Gallery of Art, Smithsonian, 1978-1980 (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1980.6. Lyman Allyn Museum (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1980.7. Meredith Long & Company, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1980.8. Hirschl & Adler Galleries, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1980.9. Albany Institute of History and Art (2 folders) (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1980.10. Fraunces Tavern Museum, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 2)
      Includes photographic prints of the requested item(s) and exhibition brochure.
    - OLR-1980.11. Bergdorf Goodman (Offsite-box 2)
    - Library: Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum, Smithsonian, 1980 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Library: New Jersey State Museum, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Unfulfilled loans, 1980 (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1981.1. Roberson Center for the Arts & Sciences (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1981.2. Nassau County Museum of Fine Art, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1981.3. The Katonah Gallery, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 2)
      Includes a photographic print of the requested item(s) and exhibition catalogue.
    - OLR-1981.4. The Library of Congress (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1981.5. Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 2)
      Includes a color transparency of the requested item(s).
    - OLR-1981.6. The Lyndon Baines Johnson Library-Museum (Offsite-box 2)
    - OLR-1981.7. Birmingham Museum of Art, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1981.8. The Heckscher Museum (Offsite-box 3)
    - OL-R1981.9. Chanticleer Pottery (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1981.10. Amon Carter Museum, 1980-1982 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1981.11. Albany Institute of History and Art, 1981, 1983 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1981.12. Daughters of the American Revolution Museum, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 3)
      Includes a photographic print of the requested item(s) and booklets associated with the exhibition.
    - OLR-1981.13. Citizen's Board Dinner (Offsite-box 3)
      This folder was pulled for staff use and not returned.
    - OLR-1981.14. Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum, Smithsonian (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1981.15. Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum, Smithsonian (Offsite-box 3)
    - Museum: Queens County Farm Museum, 1981 (Offsite-box 3)
    - Museum: The Montreal Museum of Fine Arts, 1979-1981 (Offsite-box 3)
    - Museum: Yager Museum of Art and Culture, Hartwick College, 1981-2006 (Offsite-box 49)
      Concerns a long-term loan of 1818.1 Portrait of John Christopher Kunze, D.D. by John Wesley Jarvis from 1981 to 2006. Includes a photographic print of the requested item(s).
    - Unfulfilled loans, 1981 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.1. National Portrait Gallery, Smithsonian, 1981-1983 (Offsite-box 3)
      Includes exhibition brochure.
    - OLR-1982.2. Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1981 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.3. The Art Museum, Princeton University, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.4. Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, 1981-1983 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.5. Museum of the City of New York, 1981-1983 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.6. Grey Art Gallery, New York University, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.7. Grey Art Gallery, New York University (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.8. The Berkshire Museum (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.9. Caswell-Massey Co. Ltd. (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.10. Cedar Rapids Museum of Art (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.11. Albany Institute of History and Art, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.12. Fraunces Tavern Museum, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1982.13. Danforth Museum (Offsite-box 3)
    - Unfulfilled loans, 1982, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3)
    - OLR-1983.1. National Portrait Gallery, Smithsonian, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 4)
    - OLR-1983.2. Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission (Offsite-box 4)
    - OLR-1983.3. The Rhode Island Historical Society, 1982-1985 (Offsite-box 4)
      Includes the subsequent transfer of the object from Rhode Island direct to the Smithsonian National Portrait Gallery in 1984 for their China Trade exhibition.
    - OLR-1983.4. Museum of American Folk Art, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 4)
    - OLR-1983.5. Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1981-1984 (Offsite-box 4)